Guide to the F. O. Matthiessen Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
F. O. Matthiessen papers
1900-1964
YCAL MSS 495
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
23.76
(22 boxes)
The F. O. Matthiessen Papers document the work and life of historian, literary critic, and educator F. O. Matthiessen. The papers consist of personal and professional correspondence, drafts of writings, notebooks, agendas, teaching materials, photographs, printed materials, and personal papers, spanning the years 1900-1964. The bulk of the collection consists of Matthiessen's correspondence and writing drafts and original material collected by Louis Hyde in the process of researching and writing Rat & the Devil: Journal Letters of F. O. Matthiessen and Russell Cheney.
Matthiessen, F. O. (Francis Otto), 1902-1950
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Louis K. Hyde, 1967; George Abbott White, 1967, 1983, 1984, 1985, 1991; and Richard W. Hyde, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm service copy is available for: I. 1967 Acquisitions, Other Papers, Financial papers, 1948-1950 (film number 955).
F. O. Matthiessen, 1902-1950
Francis Otto Matthiessen, American historian, literary critic and educator. He was born on February 19, 1902 in Pasadena, California. Matthiessen graduated from Yale University in 1923, was a Rhodes Scholar at Oxford University, and received his doctorate from Harvard in 1927. He taught at Harvard University from 1929-1950 and chaired its undergraduate program in history and literature. Matthiessen's notable works concern T. S. Eliot, the James family (Alice James, Henry James, Henry James Sr., and William James), and writers of the American Renaissance, including Ralph Waldo Emerson, Sarah Orne Jewett, Sinclair Lewis, Herman Melville, Henry David Thoreau, and Walt Whitman. He is best known for his book, American Renaissance: Art and Expression in the Age of Emerson and Whitman (1941).
Matthiessen's life partner was the painter Russell Cheney and the couple shared a cottage in Kittery, Maine. Matthiessen kept his personal life quite private and wished for most of his colleagues to not know he was gay. His friends, however, maintained close relationships with him and Cheney throughout their years together. Cheney died in 1945 of mesenteric thrombosis and Matthiessen never recovered from his death. He committed suicide by jumping from a window in 1950.
Scope and Contents
The F. O. Matthiessen Papers document the work and life of historian, literary critic and educator F. O. Matthiessen. The papers consist of personal and professional correspondence, drafts of writings, notebooks, agendas, teaching materials, photographs, printed materials, and personal papers, spanning the years 1900-1964. The bulk of the collection consists of Matthiessen's correspondence and writing drafts and original material collected by Louis Hyde in the process of researching and writing Rat and the Devil: Journal Letters of F. O. Matthiessen and Russell Cheney. Writings shed light on Matthiessen's creative process and include handwritten and typescript drafts and printed versions of writings, including his books American Renaissance: Art and Expression in the Age of Emerson and Whitman, "Oliver Goldsmith as Essayist and Critic," Sarah Orne Jewett, and Theodore Dreiser. Correspondence includes letters from friends and colleagues regarding his writings, and personal and professional matters. Material collected by Louis Hyde in the course of his research includes original correspondence between Matthiessen and Cheney, with some photocopies.
Arrangement
Organized into seven groupings: I. 1967 Acquisitions, 1913-1964. II. January 1967 Acquisition, 1900-1955. III. September and October 1983 Acquisitions, 1901-1955. IV. June 1984 Acquisition, 1930-1931. V. April 1985 Acquisition, 1941-1949. VI. February 1991 Acquisition, 1941. VII. June 1995 Acquisition, 1924-1945.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Cheney, Russell, 1881-1945; Hyde, L. K. (Louis K..) ( Rat & the devil); Matthiessen, F. O. (Francis Otto), 1902-1950
- 1967 Acquisitions, 1913-1964, undated; 1; 4.42; (5 boxes)
  Custodial History
  Gift of George Abbott White and Louis K. Hyde, 1967.
  Arrangement
  Organized into two series: Correspondence with F. O. Matthiessen and Other Papers.
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Filed at the end of the series is correspondence with only first names identified and correspondence grouped together by subject.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Formerly classified as Za Matthiessen and Uncat ZA MS Matthiessen.
  - Correspondence with F.O. Matthiessen
    - "A" general, 1942-1949; 3 (Box 1)
    - Aaron, Dan, 1939-1949; 2 (Box 1)
    - Academy of American Poets, 1946-1949 (Box 1)
    - Aiken, Conrad, 1945-1949 (Box 1)
    - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1944-1949; 4 (Box 1)
    - Allen, Gay Wilson, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Allen, Harvey, 1935 (Box 1)
    - American Men of Letters Series, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Anderson, Lee, 1945 (Box 1)
    - Andover Press, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - Arvin, Newton, 1939-1943; 2 (Box 1)
    - Ashbery, John, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Auchincloss, Louis, 1945 (Box 1)
    - Auden, W. H., 1943-1945; 2 (Box 1)
    - "B" general, 1929-1950; 4 (Box 1)
    - Bacon, Leonard, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Baker, Howard and Dorothy, 1940-1949; 3 (Box 1)
    - Barber, C. L., 1939-1949 (Box 1)
    - Beach, Joseph W., 1945 September 21 (Box 1)
    - Becket, G. Campbell, 1925-1942 (Box 1)
    - Benet, Stephen Vincent, undated (Box 1)
    - Bennett, J. D., 1941-1946; 2 (Box 1)
    - Bentley, Eric, 1945-1949 (Box 1)
    - Blackmur, R. P., 1946 (Box 1)
    - Boorstin, D. J., 1936-1947 (Box 1)
    - Bourjaily, Vance, 1948 December 2 (Box 1)
    - Bowron, B, 1945-1949 (Box 1)
    - Braybrooke, Neville, 1946 October 19 (Box 1)
    - Brooks, Cleanth, 1936-1942 (Box 1)
    - Brown, Alice, 1928 June 13 (Box 1)
    - Buckley, Jonathan O., 1925-1945; 2 (Box 1)
    - Bynner, Witter, 1946-1949 (Box 1)
    - "C" general, 1929-1949; 4 (Box 1)
    - Canby, Henry S., 1935-1948 (Box 1)
    - Cane, Melville, 1945 October 5 (Box 1)
    - Cather, Willa, 1926-1927 (Box 1)
    - Charrat, William, 1946 May 19 (Box 1)
    - Cheney, Clifford, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    - Cheney, Dorothy, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Cheney, Elizabeth, 1929 April 19 (Box 1)
    - Cheney, Helen, 1946 December 5 (Box 1)
    - Cheney, Howell, 1946 November 14 (Box 1)
    - Cheney, Louise, 1946 November 16 (Box 1)
    - Cheney, Marjory, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    - Cheney, Mary, 1947 January 7 (Box 1)
    - Cheney, Russell, 1913-1947; 2 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes photograph
    - Cheney, Ward, undated (Box 1)
    - Citizens' Victory Committee for Harry Bridges, 1941-1944; 6 (Box 1)
    - Coburn, Alvin Langdon, 1946 December 2 (Box 1)
    - Coffin, William Sloane, 1949 January 3 (Box 1)
    - Conant, James B., 1938-1943; 2 (Box 1)
    - Coolidge, Julian, 1929 (Box 1)
    - Cooper, John Sherman, 1925-1938 (Box 1)
    - Cooper Union, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Cowley, Malcolm, 1938-1948 (Box 1)
    - Craig, Hardin, 1938 November 22 (Box 1)
    - Crockett, John, 1949 February 15 (Box 1)
    - Cunningham, Hugh T., 1934-1949 (Box 1)
    - Current, Garcia, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
    - "D" general, 1925-1950; 4 (Box 1)
    - Davenport, Russell, 1929-1946 (Box 1)
    - Davis, Jerome, 1936 November 18 (Box 1)
    - Day, Huntington T., 1925-1947 (Box 1)
    - Deutsch, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Devoto, Bernard, 1936-1938 (Box 1)
    - Dorman, Florence and H. H., 1936-1949; 2 (Box 1)
    - Doubleday & Company Inc., 1946 (Box 1)
    - Durand, Dana, 1931 December 6 (Box 1)
    - "E" general, 1929-1949; 3 (Box 2)
    - Eberhart, Richard, 1945-1949 (Box 2)
    - Edel, Leon, 1945-1949 (Box 2)
    - Einstein, Albert, 1948 (Box 2)
    - Elias, Robert H., 1938-1949 (Box 2)
    - Eliot, T. S., 1938-1945 (Box 2)
    - Engel, Monroe, 1943-1944 (Box 2)
    - Engle, Paul, 1944 (Box 2)
    - "F" general, 1924-1948; 3 (Box 2)
    - Farrell, James T., 1946 (Box 2)
    - Finch, John, 1939-1949; 2 (Box 2)
    - Finley, John, 1940-1945 (Box 2)
    - Fitzgerald, Barry, 1944-1949 (Box 2)
    - Flint, Robert, 1943-1944 (Box 2)
    - Foster, Max, 1927-1941 (Box 2)
    - Francis, Paul, 1944-1946 (Box 2)
    - Freeman, Mary E. Wilkinson, 1928 August 14 (Box 2)
    - French, Robert Dudley, 1920-1945 (Box 2)
    - "G" general, 1939-1950; 3 (Box 2)
    - Gabrieli, V., 1949; 2 (Box 2)
    - Gallup, Donald, 1938 (Box 2)
    - Geist, Stanley, 1943-1945 (Box 2)
    - George, William, 1944-1949; 2 (Box 2)
    - Ginger, Ray, 1949 November (Box 2)
    - Goodwin, Richard M., 1936 (Box 2)
    - Granville-Barker, Harley, 1940-1951 (Box 2)
    - Gray, Charlie, 1950 January 18 (Box 2)
    - Greenslet, Ferris, 1934 (Box 2)
    - Gregory, Horace, 1944 May 11 (Box 2)
    - "H" general, 1929-1950; 4 (Box 2)
    - Harap, Louis, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
    - Harvard University, 1930-1950 (Box 2)
    - Heller, Clemens, 1944-1949 (Box 2)
    - Heringman, Bernie, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Hicks, Granville, 1938-1941 (Box 2)
    - Houghland, Willard, 1928-1940 (Box 2)
    - Houghton Mifflin, 1945-1947 (Box 2)
    - Houghton, Walter, 1929-1946 (Box 2)
    - Howe, Irving, 1948 October (Box 2)
    - Howe, Mark A. DeWolfe, 1928-1931 (Box 2)
    - Huberman, Leo, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
    - Hutchins, Robert M., 1936-1943 (Box 2)
    - Hyde, Louis K., 1925-1950; 13 (Box 2)
    - "I" general, 1934-1949 (Box 2)
    - "J" general, 1944-1950; 2 (Box 2)
    - Jackson, Gabriel, 1940-1945; 3 (Box 2)
    - James, Henry, 1944-1946 (Box 2)
    - Jewett, Sarah Orne, 1928; 2 (Box 2)
    - John Reed Club (Box 2)
    - Jones, Howard Mumford, 1941-1947 (Box 2)
    - "K" general, 1928-1949; 4 (Box 2)
    - Kang, Yang, 1945-1946 (Box 2)
    - Katz, Evalyn, 1944-1946 (Box 2)
    - Kazin, Alfred, 1947-1949 (Box 2)
    - Kazin, Pearl, 1949 August 27 (Box 2)
    - Kinoy, Arthur, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
    - Kipling, Rudyard, 1928 August 23 (Box 2)
    - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1941-1947 (Box 2)
    - Knapp, Emily, 1946-1949 (Box 2)
    - Kollar, H. C., 1926-1931 (Box 2)
    - Kreymborg, Alfred, 1949 January (Box 2)
    - "L" general, 1936-1949; 4 (Box 2)
    - Lamont, Corliss, 1942 November 23 (Box 3)
    - Lask, Harold J., 1948-1949 (Box 3)
    - Laughlin, James, 1943-1950 (Box 3)
    - Leontief, Wassily, 1950 January 16 (Box 3)
    - Levenson, J. C., 1945-1950 (Box 3)
    - Levin, Harry, 1934-1949; 2 (Box 3)
    - Lewis, R. W. B., 1940-1948 (Box 3)
    - Lowes, John, 1924-1937 (Box 3)
    - Luckey, Yorick, 1924-1943 (Box 3)
    - Lusk, William T., 1946 November 14 (Box 3)
    - Lynd, Helen, 1944-1950 (Box 3)
    - "M" general, 1929-1949; 5 (Box 3)
    - McCaffery, Harry, 1937-1946 (Box 3)
    - McLane, James, 1931-1944 (Box 3)
    - MacLeish, Archibald, 1939-1945 (Box 3)
    - Macmillan Company, 1941 (Box 3)
    - McWilliams, Carey, 1930-1949 (Box 3)
    - Maddocks, Melvin, 1944-1947 (Box 3)
    - Manning, Fred and Helen, 1945 (Box 3)
    - Marx, Leo, 1945-1950 (Box 3)
    - Matthiessen, F. O., 1924-1950; 2 (Box 3)
    - Matthiessen, F. W., 1944-1947 (Box 3)
    - Matthiessen, R. W., 1943 November 13 (Box 3)
    - Matthiessen, Bill and Alvah, 1936-1941 (Box 3)
    - Matthiessen, Dwight and Muriel, 1927-1948 (Box 3)
    - Matthiessen, Eda, 1929 (Box 3)
    - Matthiessen Family, 1940; 2 (Box 3)
    - Matthiessen, Jean, 1927-1942 (Box 3)
    - Matthiessen, Lucille, 1927-1945; 2 (Box 3)
    - Melhorn, Jean, 1940-1948 (Box 3)
    - Mellquist, Jerome, 1933-1949; 4 (Box 3)
    - Melville-Metcalf, E., 1934 June 11 (Box 3)
    - Merriman, Roger B., 1929-1945 (Box 3)
    - Metcalf, Tom, 1945-1946 (Box 3)
    - Middlebury Conference 1944 (Box 3)
    - Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1948 January 29 (Box 3)
    - Miller, Perry, 1937-1944 (Box 3)
    - Moore, Marianne, 1948 December 13 (Box 3)
    - Morgan, Ed, 1937-1941 (Box 3)
    - Morison, Samuel Eliot, 1936 (Box 3)
    - Morris, Wright, 1942-1948 (Box 3)
    - Munn, James, 1929-1941 (Box 3)
    - Murdoch, Laurette and Kenneth, 1926-1949, undated; 8 (Box 3)
    - Museum of Modern Art, 1947 December 3 (Box 3)
    - "N" general, 1940-1949; 4 (Box 3)
    - Neubrand, H. G. (Box 3)
    - Neubrand, Louise, 1940-1948 (Box 3)
    - New Republic, 1929-1948 (Box 3)
    - Newhall, Nancy, 1939 (Box 3)
    - Nelson, Truman, 1949, undated (Box 3)
    - New York Times, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
    - New York Trust, 1943-1947; 5 (Box 3)
    - The New Yorker, 1943 July 9 (Box 3)
    - Nin, Anais, undated (Box 3)
    - Nobel Prize Committee, 1948 (Box 3)
    - Norman, Charles, 1945 (Box 3)
    - Norton & Company Inc., 1930-1949 (Box 3)
    - Notestein, Wallace, 1930 December 12 (Box 3)
    - "O" general, 1935-1949; 4 (Box 3)
    - O'Connor, William Van, 1946-1949 (Box 3)
    - Olson, Charles, 1939-1947 (Box 3)
    - "Oxford Letter", undated (Box 3)
    - Oxford (University of), 1937-1950; 4 (Box 3)
    - Oxford University Press, 1934-1947 (Box 3)
    - "P" general, 1928-1949; 4 (Box 3)
    - Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1939-1949 (Box 3)
    - Pelly, Bernard, undated (Box 3)
    - Perkins, Elliot, 1933 January 22 (Box 3)
    - Perkins, Maxwell E., 1946 May 6 (Box 3)
    - Perry, Ralph Barton, 1937 (Box 3)
    - Poggioli, Renato, 1947 May 1 (Box 3)
    - Pollak, Louis, 1943-1945 (Box 3)
    - Poor, Henry, 1944 (Box 3)
    - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1945-1946 (Box 3)
    - Pratt, George, 1929-1941 (Box 3)
    - Praz, Mario, 1949 August 27 (Box 3)
    - Price, Frederic Newlin, 1946-1947 (Box 4)
    - Princeton University, 1946-1947 (Box 4)
    - Putnam, Cordelia, undated (Box 4)
    - Putnam, Phelps and Una, 1926-1949, undated; 3 (Box 4)
    - Quinn, Kerker, 1941 August 5 (Box 4)
    - "R" general, 1936-1949; 5 (Box 4)
    - Rackliffe, John, 1947, undated (Box 4)
    - Rahv, Philip, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
    - Rajan, B., 1944-1946 (Box 4)
    - Ransom, John Crowe, 1942-1949, undated; 3 (Box 4)
    - Rhodes Scholarship, 1935-1937 (Box 4)
    - Richards, I. A., 1927-1949 (Box 4)
    - Roberts, Preston, 1943-1945 (Box 4)
    - Rukeyser, Muriel, 1942-1944; 2 (Box 4)
    - "S" general, 1941-1949; 4 (Box 4)
    - Samuel Adam's School for Social Studies, 1945 (Box 4)
    - Sargent, Porter, 1940-1948 (Box 4)
    - Sarton, Mary, 1949, undated (Box 4)
    - Schacht, Marshall, 1949 (Box 4)
    - Schlatter, Richard, 1934-1948 (Box 4)
    - Schlefer, Mark, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
    - Schlesinger, Arthur Jr., 1941 July 30 (Box 4)
    - Schomer, Howard, 1938-1946; 4 (Box 4)
    - Schorer, Mark, 1946 October 13 (Box 4)
    - Schwartz, Delmore, 1940-1943; 2 (Box 4)
    - Sedgwick, William, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
    - Seidman, Bob, 1941 October 28 (Box 4)
    - Seymour, Charles, 1936-1949 (Box 4)
    - Shapiro, Karl, 1945-1949; 3 (Box 4)
    - Shattuck, Roger, 1946 June 20 (Box 4)
    - Sillen, Samuel, 1948 October 11 (Box 4)
    - Silone, Ignazio, 1949 April 14 (Box 4)
    - Silverman, undated (Box 4)
    - Silvette, Herbert, 1939-1940 (Box 4)
    - Simmons, Ernest J., 1940-1948 (Box 4)
    - Sloane, William, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
    - Smith, Henry Nelson, 1946-1947 (Box 4)
    - Spencer, Theodore, 1929-1948; 3 (Box 4)
    - Spender, Stephen, undated (Box 4)
    - Spiller, Robert, 1943-1945; 3 (Box 4)
    - Stange, Bob, 1950 January 17 (Box 4)
    - Steffens, Pete, 1946-1949 (Box 4)
    - Steinhardt, Fred, 1929-1931 (Box 4)
    - Stephens, Holly, 1964, undated (Box 4)
    - Stewart, Donald Ogden, 1949 July 5 (Box 4)
    - Stewart, Randall, 1939 December 10 (Box 4)
    - Stronfort, Lionel, 1924-1945 (Box 4)
    - Summers, Joseph, 1942-1950; 4 (Box 4)
    - Sweeny, John, 1946-1948 (Box 4)
    - Sweezy, Paul M., 1946-1949 (Box 4)
    - "T" general, 1944-1948; 2 (Box 4)
    - Taggard, Genevieve, 1945 (Box 4)
    - Tate, Allen, 1935-1948 (Box 4)
    - Taylor, Harold, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Tighe, Richard L., 1927-1933 (Box 4)
    - Tinker, Chauncey Brewster, 1950 March 1 (Box 4)
    - Tufts, Jeanne, undated (Box 4)
    - "U" general, 1942-1949; 2 (Box 4)
    - University of Pennsylvania, 1947 (Box 4)
    - Untermeyer, Louis, 1949 April 2 (Box 4)
    - "V" general, 1945-1949; 2 (Box 4)
    - VanDoren, Mark, 1949 March 23 (Box 4)
    - Van Gelden, Robert, 1944-1946 (Box 4)
    - Venable, Vernon, 1945-1947 (Box 4)
    - Villa, Jose Garcia, 1946 May 27 (Box 4)
    - Voorhis, Jerry, 1925-1948 (Box 4)
    - "W" general, 1939-1949; 4 (Box 4)
    - Walker, Charlie, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Wallace Campaign, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
    - Wallace, Henry A., 1948 (Box 4)
    - Walsh-Sweezy memo, 1937 (Box 4)
    - Wanning, Andrew, 1936 May 1 (Box 4)
    - Warren, Austin, undated (Box 4)
    - Warren, Robert Penn, 1942-1949; 2 (Box 4)
    - Wheeler, "Nud", 1945 July 13 (Box 4)
    - Wheelock, John Hall, 1946-1949 (Box 4)
    - Whitney, Edward, 1929-1939 (Box 4)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1940-1946 (Box 4)
    - Wilbur, Richard, 1948 December (Box 4)
    - Wilder, Thorton, 1949 March 24 (Box 4)
    - Williams, William Carlos, 1949 (Box 4)
    - Willkie, Wendell, 1942 November 6 (Box 4)
    - Wilson, Edmund, 1929-1944 (Box 4)
    - Wilson, F.P., 1931-1949 (Box 4)
    - Wilson, Gil, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
    - Winter, Ella, 1946-1949 (Box 4)
    - Woodhouse, A. S. P., 1944 (Box 4)
    - Worcester Art Museum, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Wyle, I.R., 1935 Septemnber 18 (Box 4)
    - "X-Y-Z" general, 1949 (Box 4)
    - Yale University, 1926-1949 (Box 4)
    - Zabel, M. D., 1939-1950; 2 (Box 4)
    - Zesmer, David, 1948 September 15 (Box 4)
    - First name only
      - "A" general, undated (Box 4)
      - "B" general, 1939, undated (Box 4)
      - "C" general, 1926, 1939 (Box 4)
      - "D" general, 1937-1949 (Box 4)
      - "F" general, undated (Box 4)
      - "G" general, 1940-1948 (Box 4)
      - "H" general, 1945 July 21 (Box 4)
      - "Ian", 1934, undated (Box 4)
      - "J" general, 1924-1945 (Box 4)
      - "K" general, 1935-1941 (Box 4)
      - "N" general, 1941, July 25 (Box 4)
      - "R" general, 1928-1949 (Box 4)
      - "S" general, 1941 March 26 (Box 4)
      - "T" general, 1929-1949 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence regarding
      - Alternative education, 1950 March 1 (Box 4)
      - Cheney, Russell, 1941-1947 (Box 4)
      - Dreiser, Theodore, 1949-1950 (Box 4)
      - Harvard Teachers' Union, 1935-1947 (Box 5)
      - James, Henry, 1945-1948 (Box 5)
      - Kenyon School, 1948-1949 (Box 5)
      - Melville Society, 1943-1945; 2 (Box 5)
      - Olivet College, 1940-1949; 2 (Box 5)
      - Prague, 1947 (Box 5)
      - Salzburg Seminar, 1947-1949 (Box 5)
      - Skull and Bones, 1925-1929 (Box 5)
      - Student Recommendations, 1940 (Box 5)
      - Unidentified and unsorted correspondence, 1942-1948, undated (Box 5)
- Other Papers
  - Various notes and writings, undated; 4 (Box 22)
  - Financial papers, 1948-1950 (Box 22)
- January 1967 Acquisition, 1900-1955, undated; 2; 4.68; (7 boxes)
  Gift of Louis K. Hyde, 1967
  Organized in six series: Student Materials, Teaching Materials, Writings, Other Papers, Photographs, and Printed Materials.
  Formerly classified as Uncat ZA MS 206.
  This acquisition consists of Matthiessen's student notebooks; teaching notes and assignments, drafts of many works, including American Renaissance, "Oliver Goldsmith as Essayist and Critic," Sarah Orne Jewett, and Theodore Dreiser; agendas; correspondence; professional and personal papers including research notes, Matthiessen's will, and "Papers found in Matthiessen's bureau drawers;" photographs; and printed material.
  - Student Materials
    - Unidentified notebooks, undated; 2 (Box 6)
    - New College notebook, undated; 2 (Box 6)
    - Yale University notebooks, 1919-1923; 6 (Box 6)
    - Notebooks from Matthiessen's time in France, undated (Box 6)
    - Matthiessen's exam blue books for English course, 1926, 1933 (Box 6)
    - Matthiessen's Shakespeare course notes, undated (Box 6)
  - Teaching Materials
    - Harvard teaching materials, 1930-1947; 17 (Box 6)
    - Salzburg seminar materials and correspondence, 1947-1948; 6 (Box 7)
    - Czechoslovakia seminar materials and correspondence, 1948; 6 (Box 7)
    - Materials regarding trip to Budapest from Salzburg, 1947 November (Box 7)
    - English assignments and typescript carbon writing drafts, undated (Box 7)
    - Kenyon School of Letters summer seminar on Modern American Poetry, notes, 1948 (Box 7)
  - Writings
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - The Achievement of T.S. Eliot, reviews, 1935 (Box 7)
    - American Renaissance, photographs, drafts, notes, and reviews, 1941; 6 (Box 7)
    - "Eliot's Quartets," printed version, reprinted from The Kenyon Review, Spring 1943 (Box 7)
    - From the Heart of Europe, reviews, 1948 (Box 7)
    - "Oliver Goldsmith as Essayist and Critic: Thesis submitted for the Degree of Bachelors of Literature, Yale University (1923)," drafts and notes, 5 (Box 8)
    - "The Humanities in War Time," printed version, reprint of 1943 Harvard Album (Box 7)
    - "Instruction and Amusement: The Mid-Eighteenth Century Essay," typescript draft, undated (Box 7)
    - Michael Wigglesworth: a Puritan Artist, notes and drafts, 1928 (Box 7)
    - The Notebooks of Henry James, notes, photographs, drafts, and reviews, 1955; 3 (Box 7)
    - "A Record of the Transcontinental Auto Trip Made by J. L. Pond, H. B. Tyson, and F. O. Matthiessen, Summer of 1919," typescript draft (Box 7)
      Accompanied by letter from Pond to Leo Marx, 1969 November 10
      Gift of John Lawrence Pond, September 1970
    - "The Responsibilities of the Critic," printed version, reprint of Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review, 1949 July 30 (Box 7)
    - Sarah Orne Jewett, draft and reviews, 1929; 3 (Box 7)
    - Selected Poems by Herman Melville, reviews, 1947 (Box 7)
    - Theodore Dreiser, drafts, 1951; 2 (Box 7)
    - "To the Memory of Phelps Putnam," printed version, reprint from The Kenyon Review, Winter 1949 (Box 7)
    - Typescript drafts of various book reviews by Matthiessen, undated (Box 7)
    - Bibliographies and notes on writings and teaching, undated (Box 7)
  - Other papers
    - Agendas, 1930-1948; 6 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence
      - The American Bookman to unidentified, undated (Box 7)
      - Atkin, W.G., 1939 March 10 (Box 7)
        Accompanied by issue of Helicon (undated)
      - Kazin, Alfred (photocopies), undated (Box 7)
      - Pitkin, Emily Knapp (photocopies), 1949-1951 (Box 7)
      - Shapiro, Karl, 1952, undated (Box 7)
      - From Dirk J. Struik to Maurice Tobin, undated (Box 7)
      - Unidentified fragment, undated (Box 7)
    - Professional papers
      - Biographical entry for Who's Who, undated (Box 9)
      - Submission guidelines for Dictionary of Literary and Dramatic Criticism, undated (Box 9)
      - Research notes, undated (Box 9)
      - Henry James bibliography, undated (Box 9)
      - Material on censorship, 1942-1944, undated (Box 9)
    - Personal papers
      - Will, 1926 (Box 9)
      - "Papers found in Matthiessen's bureau drawers, 1950 August 16", undated; 3 (Box 9)
        Includes personal notes, letters, and other papers. One folder includes Sarah Orne Jewett letters.
      - Russell Cheney wood block print, undated (Box 9)
      - "Cheney mailing list additions", undated (Box 9)
      - Index cards with names, addresses, and writing notes, undated (Box 10)
  - Photographs
    Photographs are also in the Writings series.
    - "Matthiessen: Family Record and Album", undated (Box 11)
    - Various photographs, undated (Box 11)
    - Passport, 1923 (Box 11)
    - Portraits of Matthiessen by Bachrach, undated (Box 11)
    - Portraits of Matthiessen by John Brook, undated (Box 11)
    - Snapshots of Kittery, cats, woods, and the sea, undated (Box 11)
    - Photographs used in publication of Rat and the Devil, with labels by Hyde, undated (Box 11)
  - Printed material